Guide to the James G. Harbord Papers 1902-1949 MS 1493
New-York Historical Society
- Series II: Military papers
  - Subseries II.1: Correspondence, reports and diary
    Each of these cables is signed by Kerr, McCain, or Harris; several messages from March, Marcorps, Baker; others include Williams, Garfield, Goethals, Keppel, Dockery, Pershing, Crowell, Biddle, Wheeler, Marks. The messages are addressed to "Pershing Amexforce" General Headquarters A.E.F.
    A significant number of cablegrams are absent, noted only by alphanumeric code on otherwise blank sheets, noting that there were "no copies made." Most of these cablegrams refer to "casuals" or "casualties," though others are simply marked "confidential."
    The majority of cablegrams are seeking/relaying orders about personnel; procedure; release of and communication with prisoners; requests for money and/or goods; discharge of soldiers; aid for military families of fallen soldiers; notifications sent to soldiers while abroad (mostly related to death of family members); foreign infantrymen & U.S. naturalization/citizenship (Mexican, Cuban, Swedish, Norwegian, Spanish; Panamanian, Danish, Russian, Colombian, Netherlands, Brazilian, Portuguese, Bulgarian); officers available to work different positions (veterinarian, ophthalmologist, flight surgeon); delays in mail; hospital organization; service award and rank announcements; requests for more officers; expense reports; machinery requests; shipments of Christmas presents; deaths from disease; epidemic in France; transportation authorization (including of military wives and children); funds transferred to Commanding General trust in Paris; prevention of disease spread upon reentry to U.S.; new system for baggage records (in response to lost baggage complaints); reassignments/moving of officers; statements to be read to soldiers; missing cabled money to soldier; verification of status of health and/or causes of death; Christmas greetings from Baker and March; service records; issues with notifying family of death/illness; uniform regulations; employment of soldiers; YMCA and other welfare organizations; suitable soldiers; special assignments for soldiers continuing military service (ex: American propaganda balloons); hiring of artists overseas for lack of camera coverage; "handling soldiers of enemy-alien birth."
    Cablegrams with prefixes CA and CP (end of box II.2-II.3) include three alternate types of cablegrams different from the above type, though they still follow the chronological and alphanumeric code system. CA and CP cablegrams are sent via courier rather than cable, and both sets are addressed to the Commander in Chief or Commanding General from the Adjutant General and copied to Harbord in his capacity as Chief of Staff to Pershing. The CP cablegrams are drafts to be reviewed and sent out. Most of the CP cablegrams are in letter-form with much more detailed explanation or requests.
    The first folder in box II.3 is comprised of cablegrams from Pershing to Harbord. These are often denoted as "extract cablegrams" and are also in longer, letter-format. These cablegrams are primarily concerned with logistics about troops and supplies. There are also multiple requests for more men of specific positions and at least one request for women stenographers, typists, and clerks.
    The last three folders in box 3 are comprised of cablegrams received and sent about urgent need either for supplies or conditions of living (primarily in prison or aboard ships). Urgent supply needs include medical, artillery, clothing, uniform, beds, horses, lithographs, and cameras among other materials. Most of the messages are complaints or concerns about morale and/or health risks, but most of these claims are decided to be unfounded.
    SOS (Services of Supply) cablegrams in boxes II.4-II.5 are sent and received directly by Harbord, addressed and signed by him and the Adjutant General. These are primarily concerned with logistics of supplies, specifically artillery, machine, animals.
    Reports
    Reports and memorandums were generally authored by Harbord and cover a variety of military topics as indicated by the titles in the Box and Folder list.
    - Cablegrams A2100-A3445, 1918-1919 (Offsite-box II.1)
    - Cablegrams A813-A2009, 1918 (Box II.12)
    - Cablegrams, 1918 (Offsite-box II.3)
    - S.O.S cablegrams, 1918-1919 (Offsite-box II.4 - II.6)
    - Index to cablegrams, 1918-1919 (Offsite-box II.7)
    - S.O.S daily statistical reports, 1918-1919 (Offsite-box II.8)
    - Other S.O.S. reports (Offsite-box II.9)
    - Report of Board of Officers Appointed by S.O.S.; Report of Assistant Chief of Staff of S.O.S. with accompanying maps, 1919 (Offsite-box II.10)
    - Report of Commanding General First Army American Expeditionary Forces; Summaries of Intelligence; Field Orders, 1918-1919 (Offsite-box II.11)
    - Notes on Organization of Operations Section; Report on Organization of French H.Q., 1918-1919 (Offsite-box II.12, Folder 1)
    - Review of U.S. Artillery Program, 1918 October 4 (Offsite-box II.12, Folder 2)
    - Shipment of Troops, 1918 July-September (Offsite-box II.12, Folder 3)
    - Tank Corp Papers, 1918 September (Offsite-box II.12, Folder 4)
    - Directory of officers/organization chart, 1919 (Offsite-box II.12, Folder 5)
    - Memorandums and reports, 1917-1919 (Offsite-box II.12, Folder 6)
    - Peace celebration orders, 1919 (Offsite-box II.12, Folder 7)
    - Historical Report of Railway Artillery Reserve (Offsite-box II.13, Folder 1)
    - Second Division Northwest of Chateau Thierry, 1918 June 1-July 10 (Offsite-box II.13, Folder 2-4)
    - Report, "The U.S. in the Mediterranean", undated (Offsite-box II.13, Folder 5)
    - Report to His Excellency, Don Horacio Vasquez, President of the Dominican Republic, of the Economic Commission, circa 1929 (Offsite-box II.13, Folder 6)
    - War Report, Edited Minutes of Army-Navy Conference of Industry-Labor and Other Leaders, 1944 January 7-8 (Offsite-box II.13, Folder 7)
    - American Legion 1937 Convention Corporation (Offsite-box II.14, Folder 1-8)
    - American Legion 1937 Convention Corporation (Offsite-box II.15, Folder 1)
    - Letters and clippings regarding Second Division Reunion, 1919, 1934 (Offsite-box II.15, Folder 2)
    - War pamphlets: Estimating Tactical Field Orders and Chemical Warfare, 1909, 1936 (Offsite-box II.15, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, 1914-1919, undated (Offsite-box II.15, Folder 4)
      Includes group portraits, images of Bellau Woods and the Ceremony of Decoration with the Croix de Guerre, and a booklet of photos of Veterinary Hospital No. 9, France
    - Images of Memorial de Chateau-Thierry, France, 1937 (Offsite-box II.15, Folder 5)
    - Diary of Major General Harbord (2 copies), 1918 (Offsite-box II.15, Folder 6-7)
      Provides a very detailed account of the passage from the U.S. to Europe on the U.S.S. Baltic when America first becomes involved in World War I, particularly the danger of submarine attack, disease and hardship experienced on the boats. Describes in detail the important landing of Pershing at Liverpool. Excellent descriptions of the trenches. And while diaries were forbidden at the Front, he described the important battles in which he took part, namely during the stand of the 2nd Division near Chateau Thierry, which stopped the German invasion of Paris in June 1918, as well as the Soissons Offensive on July 18th and 19th.
    - Letters, 1918-1919 (Offsite-box II.15, Folder 8)
  - Subseries II.2: Materials from the Philippines
    This subseries contains articles and reports about various aspects of Philippine government and culture, including Islamic culture.
    - The Filipino as a Soldier, 1909-1913 (Offsite-box II.16, Folder 1)
    - Filipino Character, 1909 (Offsite-box II.16, Folder 2)
    - The Philippine Insurrection Against the United States/Copy from Insurgent Records, undated (Offsite-box II.16, Folder 3-4)
    - The Maintenance of Order in the Philippines, 1908, undated (Offsite-box II.16, Folder 5)
    - The Maintenance of Order in the Philippines, 1912, undated (Offsite-box II.17, Folder 1)
    - The Filipino: Christian, Mohammeden, Pagan (Offsite-box II.17, Folder 2-4)
    - The Strong Men of the First Decade of the American Government in the Philippines, 1913, undated (Offsite-box II.18, Folder 1)
    - The Philippines, background materials, 1904-1912 (Offsite-box II.18, Folder 2-4)
    - The First Three Philippine Assemblies, 1912-1913, undated (Offsite-box II.18, Folder 5)
    - Manners and customs of the Mohammedan Moros of the Philippines, 1914, undated (Offsite-box II.19, Folder 1-2)
    - American Accomplishment in the Philippines, 1910-1913, undated (Offsite-box II.19, Folder 3-4)
    - The Government of the Mohammedens Moros in the Philippines (Offsite-box II.20, Folder 1-2)
    - Leading Filipinos of the Day, 1913 (Offsite-box II.20, Folder 3-4)
    - Filipino Feelings toward Americans, 1902, 1911 (Offsite-box II.21, Folder 1-2)
    - Articles and speeches, 1904-1913 (Offsite-box II.21, Folder 4)
- Series III: Speeches and addresses; travel diaries
  This series includes copies of the numerous addresses Harbord gave to political and social clubs, such as the American Legion, Union League Club, Women's National Republican Club, the Republican National Committee, the Baltic Society, and the American Asiatic Association. In addition to speaking at dedication services for several war monuments, he gave talks on military topics at the Virginia Military Institute, Army War College, West Point Society, and the Military Intelligence Reserve Society. He also spoke at scientific societies, including Engineering Societies and the American Society of Mechanical Engineering. He received invitations widely to speak on the topic of the role of radio in society, the addresses of which are included here.
  Also included are several interesting journals describing Harbord's travels to Russia (1905-1906), Java (1928), and India (1930).
  - Addresses and articles, 1908, 1920-1924 (Offsite-box III.1, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook, Banquet tendered to General James G. Harbord by the Association of the Army of the United States, 1923 March 20 (Offsite-box III.1, Folder 4-5)
  - Scrapbook, "Radio's Message to Latin America," an address by General J.G. Harbord, 1927 May 1 (Offsite-box III.1, Folder 6)
  - Addresses, 1925-1929 (Offsite-box III.2, Folder 1-2)
  - Addresses, 1930 (Offsite-box III.2, Folder 2)
  - Addresses, 1931 (Offsite-box III.2, Folder 4)
  - Addresses, 1932 (Offsite-box III.2, Folder 5-7)
  - Addresses, 1933 (Offsite-box III.2, Folder 8-9)
  - Addresses on Radio, 1923-1925 (Offsite-box III.3, Folder 1-2)
  - Addresses on Radio, 1926-1931 (Offsite-box III.3, Folder 3-4)
  - Addresses on Radio, 1933-1940 (Offsite-box III.3, Folder 5-6)
  - Diary, Russia, 1905-1906 (Offsite-box III.3, Folder 7)
    Harbord wrote this diary while on a six-month leave to Russia. Interesting (and copious) details about Russian lifestyles, clothing, food, language, and customs at the turn of the century. He gives a lot of information about travel, by ship and by train.
  - Diary, Java; Diary, India, 1928; 1930 (Offsite-box III.3, Folder 8)
    Descriptions of the flora and fauna of Java in 1928. This appears to be a pleasure trip that Harbord took on his own. Lots of description of the people, customs, food, clothing, habits of the Java when part of the Dutch East Indies. Also descriptions of India in July 1930, in which he focuses quite a lot of his attention on Indians protesting against Great Britain and boycotting British goods, and supporting Gandi. Also in the folder are several informative letters, one he writes from Manchuria on October 12, 1924.
- Series IV: Publications: "The American Army in France"
  This series contains correspondence, clippings and reviews relating to Harbord's book The American Army in France, published in 1936.
  - Correspondence, 1937-1938 (Offsite-box IV.1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Offsite-box IV.1, Folder 2-4)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Offsite-box IV.1, Folder 5-6)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1932-1935 (Offsite-box IV.1, Folder 7-8)
  - Clippings, 1930's (Offsite-box IV.1, Folder 9-11)
  - List of recipients, undated (Offsite-box IV.1, Folder 12)
  - Source materials? memoranda regarding purchases and supplies, 1919 (Offsite-box IV.1, Folder 13)
  - Book proposal?, undated (Offsite-box IV.1, Folder 14)
  - Outline, corrections, drafts, 1930's, undated (Offsite-box IV.1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with recipients, 1936-1939 (Offsite-box IV.2, Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence with Little, Brown, 1935-1940 (Offsite-box IV.2, Folder 4)
  - Reviews, 1936 (Offsite-box IV.2, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper serialization, 1935 (Offsite-box IV.2, Folder 6)
  - Page proofs, undated (Offsite-box IV.2, Folder unknown container)
  - Acknowledgement letters, "American Expeditionary Forces in France", 1929 (Offsite-box IV.2, Folder 7)
- Series V: Certificates and drawings
  - Diploma from Kansas State Agricultural College, 1896 (Box OS medium, Folder Harbord OS2)
  - Certificate of Appointment as Lieutenant Colonel of Calvary, 1917 (Box OS medium, Folder Harbord OS2)
  - Drawings for Memorial to Second Division, undated (Box OS medium, Folder Harbord OS2)